Today's daf is ע"ח Ayin-Chet 78, and we are behind. We pick
up on ע"ז עמוד ב', Ayin-Zayin Amud Bet, and
we are the very last of the narrow lines. תני תנא, Tani
Tana, and the learning should be should be in the זכות zechut
of and the protection of and for the תפילה tefillah for the
wellbeing of our חיילים chayalim and חיילות chayalot and for all אחינו
ואחיותינו בני ישראל, acheinu ve'achyoteinu b'nei Yisrael, and God should just help
us bring a speedy and secure and safe end to this terrible
time that we are in the middle of.
We okay so we pick up in תני תנא Tani Tana and
we're in the middle of a discussion of the status of חללה
chalalah and זונה zonah and חלל chalal and so on for a
כהן. Kohen. And we had just been working on a ברייתא braita
that spoke about a possibility that somebody would have all of the
statuses: חללה, chalalah, זונה, zonah, אלמנה, almanah, and גרושה, grushah, and even
if you said אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al
issur that normally once a person or an object or whatever is
already forbidden, you can't have another status of prohibition take effect on
it, that this would be possible if it went in a particular
order because each one would increase the scope of the prohibition. Okay,
so that's if you held אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur
chal al issur. So now let's take a look where the גמרא
Gemara continues from that.
תני תנא קמיה דרב ששת, Tani Tana kamei d'Rav Sheshet, תני תנא
Tani Tana in front of
רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. כל שהוא ביקח הרי הוא בלא יקח. Kol
shehu b'yikach harei hu b'lo yikach. Any person, any woman that falls
into the category by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, והוא אשה בבתוליה
יקח, v'hu ishah b'betuleha yikach, that meaning that would have been theoretically
possible for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to marry had she been
a בתולה betulah and not an אלמנה, גרושה, almanah grusha, etc., would
now be forbidden in the prohibitions of
לא
יקח, lo yikach, אלמנה גרושה וחללה זונה. almanah, grushah, v'chalalah, zonah. Okay?
כל שאינו ביקח, Kol she'eino b'yikach, but a woman that even had
she been a בתולה, betulah, no had no previous marriage status, etc.,
still he could not marry her, would not have been possible to
marry, אינו בלא יקח, eino b'lo yikach, will also not be forbidden
based if she happens to be an אלמנה almanah, and a גרושה.
grushah, So that's a cute way of saying what we're trying we're
going to try to say. What are we really trying to say?
פרט לכהן גדול שבא על אחותו אלמנה. Prat l'Kohen Gadol sheba al
achoto almanah. It would exclude a case of somebody that was, let's
say, his sister who's a widow. In such a case that since
he could not marry her even if she was a virgin and
never was married before, etc., because it's a sister. So therefore, now
that she also is an אלמנה, almanah a גרושה, grushah. all these
other things, those she's not forbidden from that perspective. She's still forbidden
as his sister, but not from that perspective, which is basically a
way of saying אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al
issur. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה.
Amar lei. So this is what the תנא tana taught in front
of רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב ששת Rav Sheshet then said to
the תנא, tana, אמר ליה דאמר לך מני רבי שמעון היא. Amar
lei d'amar lach mani Rabbi Shimon hi. Who was the one that
must have told you this, or meaning whose teaching is this? This
is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דאמר אין איסור חל על איסור. d'amar
ein issur chal al issur. An איסור issur does not take effect
on another. So since she's already forbidden as his sister, she cannot
also become forbidden as an אלמנה almanah, or a גרושה grushah, or
whatever. דתניא, D'tanya, we turn in the ברייתא. braita. רבי שמעון אומר
האוכל נבילה ביום הכיפורים פטור. Rabbi Shimon omer ha'ochel neveilah b'Yom HaKippurim
patur. If somebody eats a נבילה neveilah on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
they are exempt because אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal
al issur. Now, there's a question: does it really mean there's no
prohibition at all or does it mean that you don't get lashes
a second time for that? But nevertheless, that's רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's
position. If it's something is forbidden already, it can't become forbidden another
time. אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. It
should be noted, by the way, that this is even though this
is like the paradigmatic example of that, but it is quite strange
because the איסור issur of a נבילה neveilah we think is about
the status of the object. This is forbidden food. יום כיפור Yom
Kippur is about me. I'm obligated to fast. It's not like the
food is a forbidden object. So it's actually quite fascinating because most
of the cases of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur
all have to do with when it's multiple statuses on the same
object. Anyway, that's רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position.
דתניא. D'tanya. Okay, דאי רבנן, d'ei Rabbanan, because if it's the רבנן
Rabbanan that say איסור issur is חל על איסור, chal al issur,
that if you eat a נבילה, neveilah, McDonald's hamburger on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, not only are you חייב chayav because of because it's
a treif hamburger, you're also חייב chayav for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
האמי איסור חל על איסור. Ha'amei issur chal al issur. They would
say איסור issur would take effect, and that's true that a כהן'ס
Kohen's sister who's an אלמנה almanah would also be forbidden to him
as an אלמנה. almanah כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. No. The גמרא Gemara
says no. אפילו תימא רבנן. Afilu teima Rabbanan. It could even be
the רבנן. Rabbanan. כי אמרי רבנן איסור חל על איסור הני מילי
איסור חמור על איסור קל, ki amri Rabbanan issur chal al issur
hanei mili issur chamur al issur kal, אבל איסור קל על איסור
חמור לא חייל. aval issur kal al issur chamur lo chayil.
Even if you say an איסור issur takes effect on top of
another איסור, issur, that's when the second איסור issur is weightier or
maybe the same weight, but יום כיפור Yom Kippur is weightier. יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is כרת, kares, and a נבילה, neveilah, McDonald's hamburger,
whatever, we're ignoring the cheese anyway, but that's just a simple לאו.
lav. So when will they say one איסור issur could take effect
on another? If it's of greater weight or maybe if it's of
equal weight. But here, it's an איסור קל. issur kal. The prohibition
of אלמנה almanah. is a simple לאו. lav. The prohibition of a
sister is כרת. kares. So therefore, this woman is forbidden to him
as a sister. Even the רבנן Rabbanan who say איסור חל על
איסור issur chal al issur will not be if the second one
is of a lighter weight than the original one. Okay. איכא דאמרי,
Ika d'amri, some say that he actually, that רב ששת Rav Sheshet
said back was exactly this point because it's such a nice point,
right? I mean, it seems so obvious that a light, you know,
that that this would be a case that maybe everybody could agree
on. דאמרי הא מני רבנן היא. D'amri ha mani rabanan hi. This
teaching that his sister cannot become forbidden to him as an אלמנה,
almanah that's according to the rabbis. דאמרי איסור חל על איסור, D'amri
issur chal al issur, who generally would say איסור issur would be
חל על איסור chal al issur and they're coming to tell you
in this case though, nah. וכי אמרי רבנן איסור חל על איסור
הני מילי איסור חמור על קל V'chi amri rabanan issur chal al
issur hani mili issur chamur al kal and therefore we're teaching that
when do the rabbis say it one איסור issur can take effect
on top of another if the second one is weightier. אבל איסור
קל על חמור, Aval issur kal al chamur, but if the second
one is lighter, like this case of a sister that she should
also become forbidden as an אלמנה, almanah, לא חייל, lo chayil, that
would not take effect so this is coming to teach you that
even the rabbis who say איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur would not take effect here because the second one is of
a lighter weight. דאי רבי שמעון, D'ee Rabbi Shimon, because it would
because if it was רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon there'd be no need
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to teach you this. השתא איסור חמור
על קל לא חייל. Hashta issur chamur al kal lo chayil. If
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say a weighty איסור issur doesn't take
effect on top of a light one, יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't
take effect on top of the McDonald's cheese hamburger, איסור קל על
חמור מבעיא? Issur kal al chamur mibaya? So you wouldn't have to
tell me that it would that his sister would not become forbidden
as an אלמנה. almanah, That would be so patently obvious for רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you know, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't even let
a weighty one take effect on top of a light one, sorry
on top of a light one, certainly not a light one on
top of a heavy one. So the גמרא Gemara says no, maybe
there's a חידוש chiddush here even for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
מהו דתימא, Mah u'd'teima, I might have thought איסור כהונה שאני, issur
kehunah shani, that maybe when it comes to כהן kohen it's different,
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that that's not the case. You
know, because for כהנים kohanim they have so many more prohibitions than
a normal non-כהן kohen would have, all these women that they can't
marry, maybe I would have thought that creates a special category that
the תורה Torah wants to make it forbidden even going beyond the
normal parameters of women that could be forbidden, so even a woman
that's already forbidden from another perspective, maybe the כהונה kehunah thing adds
a whole different dimension. All right, but one way or another if
a woman is forbidden as a sister, cannot also become forbidden to
a כהן kohen as a גרושה grushah or אלמנה almanah. or whatever,
and that's because even if איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur normally, it would not take effect here because the second one
is lighter, the איסור כהונה issur kehunah is always an איסור לאו,
issur lav, these other איסורים issurim of עריות arayos are you know
are כרת, kares, and we do not say just because it's an
איסור כהונה issur kehunah that will have more ability to take effect
on top of an existing איסור. issur. All right. Now, אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Pappa l'Abaye, said רב פפא Rav
Pappa to אביי, Abaye, ישראל הבא על אחותו, Yisrael ha-ba al achoto,
זונה משוי לה, zonah mashvi lah, חללה משוי לה או לא
משוי לה? chalalah mashvi lah o lo mashvi lah? So if a,
you know, a ישראל Yisrael has sex with his sister, so that
is a forbidden act, a woman becomes a זונה zonah through a
forbidden act of sex not related to כהונה. kehunah. So that makes
her into a זונה. zonah. חללה משוי לה או לא משוי לה?
Chalalah mashvi lah o lo mashvi lah? Does it make her a
חללה chalalah as well? So now here we're coming to clarify exactly
the line between זונה zonah and חללה. chalalah. All right. So we're
going to assume for now, it could be a little bit nuanced,
but for now we'll assume that a זונה zonah is created through
an act of forbidden sex, a חללה chalalah generally that is generally
applies even to non-כהנים. kohanim. A חללה chalalah is created through an
act of forbidden sex well one of two ways. Either through an
act of forbidden sex that is specific to כהנים. kohanim. So for
example a woman a גרושה grushah has sex with a כהן kohen
makes her a חללה. chalalah. Of course she was already forbidden as
a גרושה. grushah So let's take another case. An אלמנה almanah has
sex with a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So now she's also forbidden
to a normal כהן kohen as a חללה. chalalah. So through an
איסור כהונה. issur kehunah. And then there's also the case of course
of a חלל, chalal, the child of a חלל chalal is a
if it's a girl is a חללה. chalalah. So one of two
ways. All right. So one is normal איסור issur sex, the other
is sex for כהונה. kehunah. But that's the end result. Now we're
in the middle of figuring that out and we want to know
is that really true? Maybe the maybe maybe you know the act
of forbidden sex if it's generally forbidden makes her both a זונה
zonah and a חללה. chalalah. חלל חללה Chalal chalalah maybe is when
it's you know includes cases of איסורי כהונה, issurei kehunah, but maybe
the act of forbidden sex that when it's applies to normal like
non-כהנים, kohanim,
maybe that would make a woman both a זונה zonah and a
חללה. chalalah. That's the question. חללה משוי לה או לא משוי לה?
Chalalah mashvi lah o lo mashvi lah? מי אמרינן קל וחומר מחייבי
לאוין? Mi amrinan kal v'chomer me'chayavei lavin? הא השתא מחייבי לאוין הויא
חללה, Ha hashta me'chayavei lavin haviya chalalah, מחייבי כריתות לא כל שכן?
me'chayavei kerisos lo kol sheken? Do we say since a woman can
become a חללה chalalah from from acts of sex that are prohibited
by a simple לאו, lav, a simple negative prohibition, meaning let's say
let's take the case of אלמנה almanah and כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
that makes a woman a חללה, chalalah, admittedly within the world of
you know things that are forbidden to a כהן, kohen, but if
a sex prohibited by a לאו lav could make a woman a
חללה, chalalah, certainly sex prohibited by כרת kares if it's a sister
would make her a חללה. chalalah. Do we make a קל וחומר?
kal v'chomer? But it's a funny קל וחומר kal v'chomer because you
know different. categories are about different things. או דלמא, O dilma, or
do we say אין חללה אלא מאיסורי כהונה? ein chalalah ela mi'issurei
kehuna? No, you know, it's all very nice that it's weightier, but
it's a different category. חללה Chalalah is about, you know, יחלל, yichalel,
it's about desecrating the כהונה, kehuna, the קדושה, kedusha, and therefore it's
limited to prohibitions that relate to כהנים, kohanim, whereas, you know, זונה
zonah is about things that are prohibited that are, it might be
weightier, but they're, that's the category of זונה. zonah. And just because
it's a weighty prohibition does not make it a חללה chalalah as
well. Okay. So, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back, אין חללה,
ein chalalah, you know, אלא
מאיסור כהונה בלבד. ella mi'issur kehuna bilvad. Yes, the second thing you
said. חללה Chalalah is a unique כהונה kehuna status. All right. So,
and, you know, one, and one could even sort of say that
the חללה chalalah status sort of, you know, maybe starts with the
פסוק pasuk about, you know, about being מחלל זרעו mechallel zaro as
we've seen. ולא יחלל זרעו. v'lo yichallel zaro. So if you're going
to make your child from this union forbidden, it also makes the
woman forbidden. And it all is about desecrating the קדושה kedusha of
the כהונה. kehuna. Okay, that's חללה. chalalah. And then you could have
other things which are much weightier, but they're not חללה, chalalah, they're
זונה. zonah. That would be איסור כרת. issur kares. All right. Now,
whether does that apply to all איסורים issurim of sex, you know,
that, only איסורי כרת issurei kares or whatever, okay, we'll see about
some of that. But anyway, that is the fundamental difference.
Let's take a look. אמר רבא, amar Rava, מנה המילתא דאמרו רבנן
minah ha-milsa d'amru rabbanan אין חללה אלא מאיסור כהונה? ein chalalah ela
mi'issur kehuna?
So that was very nice that that was his answer. Now let's
see how we actually know that that's true. That the category of
חללה chalalah is from an act that's prohibited to a כהן, kohen,
an act of sex. דתיניא, d'tanya, we taught in a בריתא. braisa.
לא יאמר גרושה בכהן גדול ותיתי בקל וחומר מכהן
הדיוט. lo yomar grusha b'kohen gadol v'tasi b'kal v'chomer mi'kohen hedyot. Okay.
Now, by a normal כהן, kohen, it says that he can't marry,
you know, a
גרושה, grushah.
so by a normal כהן kohen it says אשה חללה וזונה לא
יקחו, ishah chalalah v'zonah lo yikachu, he can't marry a חללה chalalah
and a זונה, zonah, right? ואשה גרושה מאישה לא יקחו, v'ishah grusha
me-ishah lo yikachu, and he can't marry a woman who's divorced. Okay,
so it says חללה, chalalah, זונה zonah and גרושה, grusha, it has
חללה chalalah and זונה zonah together and then it has גרושה. grusha,
And by a כהן גדול kohen gadol it says אלמנה גרושה וחללה
זונה את אלה לא יקח,
almanah grusha v'chalalah zonah es
eileh lo yikach, right? It lists the whole four in one פסוק:
pasuk: אלמנה, almanah זונה, zonah, חללה, chalalah, אלמנה גרושה וחללה זונה, almanah
grusha v'chalalah zonah, and all of those he
cannot take. Now, the question is, the only one that's really being
added is an אלמנה. almanah, The other three are already prohibited to
him as a normal כהן. kohen. So why did the תורה Torah
have to enumerate all of them? Why couldn't it just add the
אלמנה? almanah. So let's take a look. דתיניא. d'tanya. לא יאמר גרושה
בכהן גדול. lo yomar grusha b'kohen gadol. Why does the תורה Torah
have to prohibit a כהן גדול kohen gadol to marry a גרושה?
grusha. Let it not say it. ותיתי בקל וחומר מכהן הדיוט. v'tasi
b'kal v'chomer mi'kohen hedyot. I would have made a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer from a normal כהן. kohen. You could have actually said he's
a normal כהן kohen plus, but okay,
either say it that way or as a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
ואנן אמרינן, v'anan amrinan, I would say, השתא לכהן הדיוט אסורה לכהן
גדול מי בעיא? hasha l'kohen hedyot asura l'kohen gadol mi ba'ya? If
it's prohibited to a normal כהן, kohen, certainly it should be prohibited
to a כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. למה נאמרה, lama ne'emra, so why did it say
גרושה grusha? by a כהן גדול? kohen gadol? כשם שחלוקה גרושה מזונה
וחללה בכהן הדיוט כך חלוקה בכהן גדול. k'shem she-chaluka grusha mi-zonah v'chalalah
b'kohen hedyot kach chaluka b'kohen gadol. So,
as I pointed out, by a כהן הדיוט, kohen hedyot, it says
חללה, chalalah, זונה, zonah, right? First it says לא יקחו, lo yikachu,
ואשה גרושה מאישה לא יקחו. v'ishah grusha me-ishah lo yikachu.
So גרושה grusha is held separate from חללה chalalah and זונה. zonah.
Okay, which means that you get separate מלקות malkus for גרושה. grusha
All right, each שם shem as we've seen before, you get מלקות
malkus separately. So גרושה grusha. was said separately by כהן הדיוט kohen
hedyot to teach you that, you know, if a woman has multiple
שמות shemos or whatever, each one is a separate לאו, lav, a
separate prohibition. And the same thing that's true by a כהן הדיוט,
kohen hedyot, it's also true by a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, even
though all of them are in the same פסוק, pasuk, אלמנה גרושה
וחללה זונה, almanah grusha v'chalalah zonah, to tell you that each one
is a separate לאו, lav, a separate
prohibition.
פשיטא, peshita, so the גמרא Gemara says, obviously, מגרע גרע, mi-grura,
so obviously that would be true about a גרושה, grusha right? Once
a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot gets a separate מלקות malkus for a
גרושה, grusha, and presumably for חללה chalalah and זונה, zonah, גרושה grusha,
by itself tells you that each one of those statuses is separate
מלקות. malkus. If that's true by חללה, chalalah, זונה zonah and גרושה
grusha by a normal כהן, kohen, certainly it's true by a כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, meaning you don't need it to be repeated by
a כהן גדול kohen gadol again. A כהן גדול kohen gadol is
a כהן. kohen. So obviously he would get separate מלקות malkus for
everything a כהן kohen would get. A כהן kohen would get separate
for חללה, chalalah, separate for זונה, zonah, separate for גרושה. grusha Same
by a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. If it's going to say גרושה
grusha. by כהן גדול, kohen gadol, it's telling you something new about
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, not just that he's like any other
כהן. kohen. אלא כשם שחלוקה גרושה מזונה וחללה בכהן הדיוט, ela k'shem
she-chaluka grusha mi-zonah v'chalalah b'kohen hedyot,
here's what it needs to say. By a normal כהן, kohen, it
says גרושה grusha separate from חללה chalalah and זונה, zonah, to tell
you that each one is a לאו. lav. by itself and separate
מלקות. malkus. Now, if that's true by כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, it's
true by כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So why then does the תורה
Torah say by כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, אלמנה almanah? גרושה, grusha why
does it repeat גרושה? grusha? So to tell you, כך אלמנה חלוקה
מגרושה וחללה זונה בכהן גדול. kach almanah chaluka migrusha v'chalala zona b'Kohen
Gadol. Okay, to tell you that the new one, אלמנה, almanah, is
also a separate לאו. lav. Now, you know you get a separate
מלקות malkus for אלמנה almanah by itself, which is a little funny
because if the תורה Torah had just said אלמנה, almanah, then obviously
it would have been a separate לאו. lav. But okay, for we'll
see other reasons why it had to give the whole list, אלמנה,
גרושה, חללה, זונה. almanah, grusha, chalala, zona. So the גרושה grusha in
the list is almost to remind you, to tell you each שם,
shem, each status, is a לאו lav by itself including this new
status of אלמנה. almanah. That's why it says גרושה grusha by כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, חללה למה נאמרה. chalala lama ne'emra.
Now why does it say חללה? chalala? Okay, אלמנה, גרושה, חללה, זונה.
almanah, grusha, chalala, zona. So we're going through the list. Why does
it repeat חללה chalala by כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? אין חללה אלא
מאיסור כהונה, ein chalala ela mei-issur kehuna,
to tell you that a חללה chalala comes from איסורי כהונה. issurei
kehuna. Now the way רש״י Rashi explains this is because the things
like that preceded it, right? אלמנה, גרושה, וחללה. almanah, grusha, v'chalala. So
אלמנה almanah and גרושה grusha are specific איסורי כהונה. issurei kehuna. So
חללה chalala is also specifically an איסור כהונה. issur kehuna. So the
repetition is to give you context for חללה chalala and that you
should understand that חללה chalala is based on איסורי כהונה, issurei kehuna,
right? Whereas זונה zona is
what do you call it? זונה, zona, as we've seen before, is
a concept that applies, you know, by ישראל Yisrael as well, by
non-כהנים, Kohanim, by a case of like adultery. So the fact that
חללה chalala came after אלמנה, גרושה, חללה almanah, grusha, chalala and זונה
zona did not interrupt that set, tells you that all of those
are, you know, that חללה chalala is about איסורי כהונה. issurei kehuna.
Now, so that's what we were looking for. Now we understand conceptually
the category of חללה. chalala. זונה בכהן גדול, zona b'Kohen Gadol, okay,
so now where are we? אין חללה אלא מאיסור כהונה, ein chalala
ela mei-issur kehuna, it's two lines from the bottom of עין זין
עמוד ב. ayin zayin amud beis. זונה למה נאמרה, zona lama ne'emra,
why does it say זונה, zona, repeat it by כהן גדול? Kohen
Gadol? נאמר כאן זונה ונאמר להלן זונה, ne'emar kan zona v'ne'emar lehalan
zona, because it says it here and it says it by a
normal כהן. Kohen. Okay, true. מה כאן זרעו חולין אף להלן זרעו
חולין. ma kan zaro chullin af lehalan zaro chullin. So the same
way by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it says ולא יחלל זרעו, v'lo
yechalel zaro, right? Which is the whole idea of that it affects
the child
and that the child that came from איסור כהונה issur kehuna is
a חלל. chalal. So we never had the יחלל זרעו yechalel zaro
concept said by a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, so it's to link
the two and to tell you that applies to a כהן הדיוט
Kohen Hedyot as well. Okay, אמר רב אשי: הלכך, Amar Rav Ashi:
Hilkach, therefore, based on everything we've just said, that since, you know,
or based on the fact that a חללה chalala is only from
איסורי כהונה, issurei kehuna, כהן הבא על אחותו, Kohen haba al achoso,
if a כהן Kohen has sex with his sister, זונה משוי לה,
חללה לא משוי לה. zona mashvi lah, chalala lo mashvi lah. That's
what we started, top of עין חית עמוד א. ayin ches amud
aleph. That discussing the idea of sister, okay, that makes her into
a זונה, zona, which is because it's based on a forbidden act
of sex that's אסור assur to כל ישראל, kol Yisrael, and
but does not make her into a חללה. chalala. חזר ובא עליה,
chozar u-va aleha, but now that she is a זונה, zona, right,
assuming by the way this, this assuming איסור חל איסור, issur chalal
issur, even by an איסור קל. issur kal. She was forbidden as
his sister, now she's אסור אסור assur assur to him as a
זונה. zona. Or more said, said better, for another כהן, Kohen, there's
no איסור חל, issur chalos, or for another כהן, Kohen, she was
totally permissible. Now that she's had sex with her brother, she becomes
a זונה. zona. So this woman who now has the status of
a זונה, zona, so חזר ובא
עליה, chozar u-va aleha, if now he has sex with her or
easier said if somebody else has sex with her, עשאה חללה. assa
chalala. Now it will be a זונה zona having sex with a
כהן, Kohen, which is a specific איסור כהונה issur kehuna and that
will make her into a חללה. chalala. Okay, so if it's him
then you have to say that she could be a זונה zona
on top of being a sister, gets back to the איסור חל
איסור. issur chalal issur. If it's somebody else, this woman had sex
with her brother, she became, she was considered a זונה. zona. Now
for another כהן Kohen she is forbidden, if have sex with her
that'll make her into a חללה. chalala. אמר רב יהודה: כהן גדול
באלמנה לוקה שתים. Amar Rav Yehuda: Kohen Gadol b'almanah loki shtayim. So
that was very nice in conceptualizing the difference of חללה chalala and
זונה. zona. I should say by the way that I've been saying
זונה zona is a איסור issur of sex that is אסור, assur,
you know, to כל ישראל, kol Yisrael, but it also has to
do with the fact, רמב״ם, Rambam, you know, sort of says specifically
that it's also that קידושין kiddushin is לא תופסין בה. lo tafsin
bah. That, you know, that there can't be any קידושין. kiddushin. So
for example, if a woman has sex with her husband, you know,
or a single woman has sex with a man when she's a
נידה, niddah, that's an איסור, issur, but you could have actually חלות
קידושין chalos kiddushin between the two of them. All right, and you
know there's also questions about, so therefore it would not make her
into a זונה zona or questions that say about a מצרי, Mitzri,
other types of things which are prohibited but would not prevent an
actual חלות קידושין. chalos kiddushin. So גר מצרי, ger Mitzri, so there
are other issues as well that have to be clarified in terms
of what type of forbidden sex makes a... a woman into a
זונה. zonah. Okay, let's take a look now. Now we're going to
get into a very important question about the relationship for כהנים Kohanim
between sex and marriage where the איסור issur focuses. So let's take
a look. Top of ע"ח עמוד א'. Ayin-Chet Amud Alef. אמר רב
יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, כהן גדול באלמנה לוקה שתים, Kohen Gadol b'almanah
lokeh shtayim, אחת משום לא יקח ואחת משום לא יחלל. achas mishum
lo yikach ve-achas mishum lo yechalel.
Excuse me, I jumped ahead. We're going to get to the sex
and marriage question in a little bit. Right now we're dealing with
the איסור issur of לא יקח lo yikach and לא יחלל. lo
yechalel. So now we're introducing an idea that the prohibition of כהונה
kehunah is not just about the not marrying, but also this לא
יחלל lo yechalel which normally we would read so that he should
not desecrate his child, ולא יחלל זרעו, v'lo yechalel zaro, through this
act. We're reading it as a prohibition: he shall not desecrate. And
we're also going to actually read it, as we'll see in a
minute, in two ways: He shall not make her into a חללה
chalalah and he shall not make his children חללים, chalalim, so that
actually his act, he can transgress, you know, two or three things.
He has sex with this woman who he's forbidden to; she's let's
say a גרושה. gerushah. Through this act, he makes her into a
חללה, chalalah, so he transgresses גרושה, gerushah, he transgresses לא יחלל lo
yechalel by making her into a חללה, chalalah, and presumably, we'll see
in a minute, will he even transgress לא יחלל זרעו lo yechalel
zaro because the children will be חללים? chalalim? So that is the
חידוש chiddush here of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. We'll see if we
stick with this. כהן גדול באלמנה לוקה שתים. Kohen Gadol b'almanah lokeh
shtayim. אחת משום לא יקח, achas mishum lo yikach, one because you
shall not take, ואחת משום לא יחלל. ve-achas mishum lo yechalel. Not
only did he transgress, you know, this case of the אלמנה, almanah,
of taking an אלמנה, almanah, but he also, for now we'll assume
you transgress לא יקח lo yikach in the act of sex that
follows marriage. As the גמרא Gemara said before, I'll remind you that
if a man, a כהן, Kohen, had sex with an אלמנה almanah
multiple times, the same אלמנה, almanah, he would get מלקות malkus for
each time. So the focus on now has totally been on the
act of sex. We'll talk about the act of marriage later, but
the point is that this act of sex is a transgression of
לא יקח, לא יקח lo yikach lo yikach, understanding don't have sex
in the context of marriage. So when he has sex with this
אלמנה, almanah, he transgresses לא יקח lo yikach, and he transgresses לא
יחלל lo yechalel because he turns her into a חללה. chalalah. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, ולילקי נמי משום לא יחלל זרעו? ve-lilki
nami mishum lo yechalel zaro? So how about the fact that he's
also not only going to make her a חללה, chalalah, he'll make
his kid a חלל? chalal?
So the גמרא Gemara says, בשלא גמר ביאתו. be-shelo gamar bi'aso. When
he only did not have גמר ביאה, gmar bi'ah, he did not
have full insertion of his penis, so therefore it's not considered like
it's a context in which it would lead to ejaculation, and therefore
there's not a concern of conceiving a child who is a חלל.
chalal. Now that's fascinating, right? You could have said even if you
think there's a prohibition of making your child a חלל, chalal, you
only transgress it when you actually have such a child, or you
only transgress it when, I don't know, you know, the child is
conceived or there's actual ejaculation. The גמרא Gemara here assumes that it's
all about different ways of making the act of sex forbidden. So
if we're going to read לא יחלל זרעו lo yechalel zaro as
a prohibition, we're going to read it as an act of sex
that could potentially lead to לא יחלל, lo yechalel, which means גמר
ביאה. gmar bi'ah. All right, so now, though that was not part
of רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda original statement, but now we have the
possibility of two or three prohibitions for this case of a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol with an אלמנה. almanah. We'll talk about in a
minute whether it'll apply to a normal כהן הדיוט. Kohen hedyot. Okay,
so מתיב רבא. masiv Rava. רבא Rava asked: אלמנה וגרושה לוקה משום
שני שמות. almanah u-gerushah lokeh mishum she-nei shemos.
If a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has sex with a woman who
is an אלמנה almanah and a גרושה gerushah at the same time,
he gets two sets of lashes. One for אלמנה almanah and one
for גרושה. gerushah. This is איסור חל על איסור, issur chal al
issur, but let's say they're all equal weight in this case. אלמנה
almanah and גרושה gerushah have equal weighted איסורין. issurin. So מאי לאו
שני שמות ותו לא? mai lav she-nei shemos u-so lo? It sounds
like just two, two sets of lashes, אלמנה almanah and גרושה. gerushah.
But according to you, רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, each איסור issur you
would also get, or at least for the אלמנה almanah איסור, issur,
you would get also the חללה, chalalah, because you would have turned
her into a חללה. chalalah. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא, שני
שמות על זה ושני שמות על זה. lo, she-nei shemos al zeh
u-she-nei shemos al zeh. No, each one you get two sets of
lashes, because each one, when you had this woman who was an
אלמנה almanah and a גרושה gerushah and you had sex with her,
you also made her a חללה. chalalah. So for each prohibition, for
אלמנה almanah you get אלמנה almanah and לא יחלל, lo yechalel, and
for גרושה gerushah you get גרושה gerushah and לא יחלל. lo yechalel.
Okay, which is funny because there was only once that she was
made into a חללה, chalalah, but each act, again the focus is,
since the act has the potential to make her a חללה, chalalah,
each prohibition, whether it's אלמנה almanah or גרושה, gerushah, also contains with
it an איסור issur of לא יחלל. lo yechalel. So it means
that there are two categories, but within אלמנה almanah and גרושה, gerushah,
within each category there are two sets of מלקות. malkus. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima seifa. Let's
look at the end of this ברייתא. braisa. גרושה וחלוצה אינו חייב
אלא אחת. gerushah va-chalutzah eino chayav ela achas.
If, however, this woman is not an אלמנה almanah and a גרושה,
gerushah, but that this כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is having sex with
a גרושה gerushah and a חלוצה, chalutzah, he is only liable for
one. You only get for one because חלוצה Chalutzah is understood to
be דרבנן. d'Rabanan. Okay, now according to you though it should have
said you get two sets of lashes. What does he mean you
only get one? One sounds like literally one set of lashes. It
doesn't say one שם. shem. Before it says שני שמות, shnei shemos,
you could say two categories, a גרושה grushah category and an אלמנה,
almonah, and each category is two. But here it says you get
one set of lashes, and according to you there should be lashes
for גרושה grushah plus חללה. chalalah. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, no here's
how you have to read it. אינו חייב אלא על אחת. Eino
chayav ela al achas. Okay you only get,
the first one should have said you only get for one, meaning
for one category, ולעולם שני שמות. v'olam shnei shemos. Okay, okay, and
but really you're going to get two sets of lashes. You're going
to get lashes both because of חללה, chalalah, both because of גרושה
grushah and because of לא יחלל. lo yechalel. So now we're taking
all these things that speak about one set, you know, how many
lashes you get for each שם, shem, and saying which any time
the ברייתא braisa says you get lashes for this שם shem or
that שם shem or whatever, there's always a second set that comes
along that's also because of לא יחלל. lo yechalel. All right. Now
the גמרא gemara says like this. Now we're going to sort of
speak about the חלוצה chalutzah thing for a minute. וחלוצה דרבנן? V'chalutzah
derabanan? Now is חלוצה chalutzah really rabbinic? Because you didn't get lashes
for חלוצה. chalutzah. והתניא, Vehatanya, גרושה אין לי אלא גרושה חלוצה מניין
תלמוד לומר ואישה, grushah ein li ela grushah chalutzah minayin talmud lomar
v'ishah, the extra ו, vov, ואישה גרושה מאישה, v'ishah grushah me'ishah, that
even a woman who went through חליצה, chalitzah, which is a sort
of a way of severing a quasi-marital bond through the brother-in-law, that
that's included in the prohibition. So the גמרא gemara says מדרבנן. miderabanan.
Yeah, yeah it's only rabbinic. וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא, V'krah asmachta b'alma, the
פסוק pasuk is just an אסמכתא. asmachta. Now, there are other sources
that sound like it takes the דרשה drasha seriously and thinks that
חלוצה chalutzah is a דאורייתא, d'oraita, and you could have in theory
read that the reason that גרושה grushah and חלוצה chalutzah is only
one set of lashes is חלוצה chalutzah is a type of a
גרושה, grushah, so therefore it's only one set of lashes. But that's
not what our גמרא gemara does. The general consensus is that חלוצה
chalutzah is a דרבנן, derabanan, which is what this גמרא gemara says.
Okay, so now we have seemed to come to the conclusion that
every prohibition, you know, is one that gets, that also there's a
prohibition of לא יחלל. lo yechalel. Now what needs to be said
is רש״י Rashi reads this entire סוגיא, sugya, the גמרא gemara as
you noticed spoke about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה.
almonah. Now it could have spoken about that because that's where the
פסוק pasuk says ולא יחלל זרעו. v'lo yechalel zaro. But it could,
and רש״י Rashi assumes it's not meant to limit it to that.
That this idea that you would get lashes for making the woman
into a חללה chalalah would apply for a כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot
as well, and it would not be limited to the, to, you
know, any particular scenario. That a woman who anyway was forbidden to
a כהן kohen as a גרושה grushah let's say, if she now
had sex with a כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot and he now, she
was now both a גרושה grushah and a חללה, chalalah, the כהן
הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, this would also be a set of lashes for
making her into a חללה. chalalah. That's the way רש״י Rashi reads.
Every time there's a forbidden act of sex with a כהן kohen
and a woman, it makes her into a חללה. chalalah. Maybe you
get, assuming she hadn't been a חללה chalalah before that, if it
makes her into a חללה chalalah and then there's lashes for that.
רמב״ם Rambam does not understand it that way. רמב״ם Rambam says we're
talking specifically about אלמנה almonah and כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, or at
least specifically about כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because in the case at
least of an אלמנה almonah and a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, this
woman was permissible to all כוהנים, kohanim, so the act of sex
that he had with her made her into a חללה, chalalah, made
her forbidden to other כוהנים, kohanim, which she was not until then,
until that point. That's one reason to limit it to a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. And the other reason to limit it, right, because
by any other כהן, kohen, the woman to become a חללה chalalah
would have already been forbidden. So making her also a חללה, chalalah,
if a כהן kohen has sex with a גרושה grushah or a
זונה, zonah, making her also a חללה chalalah adds a status but
it doesn't, it doesn't make her more forbidden. But a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה, almonah, if he has sex with her,
makes her a חללה, chalalah, makes her now forbidden to all כוהנים.
kohanim. So on the one hand, the effect of the act is
much bigger for a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Number two, the פסוק
pasuk לא יחלל lo yechalel is said only by the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. So רמב״ם Rambam limits this idea only to a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, not to a כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot. That's actually
quite important because for a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, because we're about
to get into the סוגיא sugya about whether the prohibition for a
normal כהן kohen focuses on marriage or sex, and we'll see how
this will play out. But if you think like רש״י Rashi that
every forbidden act of sex also is לא יחלל, lo yechalel, even
by a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, that's going to have very broad
implications that, you know, that any time a woman is made into
a חללה chalalah there's always going to be a prohibition. For רמב״ם
Rambam it is limited to a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
which really makes it moot for our
purposes. Okay, so that's question number one. Does every prohibition of a
כהן, kohen, which when the woman becomes a חללה, chalalah, are you
also transgressing לא יחלל? lo yechalel? רבא Rava says you are, even
though it's not פשט pshat of some of the סוגיות, sugyos, and
רש״י Rashi says that means for a normal כהן kohen as well,
every prohibition with a woman who's not a חללה, chalalah, whether it's
a גרושה, gerushah, זונה, zonah, whatever, would be also prohibition of לא
יחלל, lo yechalel, and רמב"ם Rambam says no, sorry, that only applies
to a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay now let's look at this
next really important debate about the focus on marriage versus sex.
Okay. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: קידש לוקה בעל לוקה קידש לוקה משום
לא יקח בעל לוקה משום לא יחלל.
Kidesh loke ba'al loke kidesh loke
mishum lo yikach ba'al loke mishum lo yechalel. So אביי Abaye says
when a, you know, when the קידושין kiddushin takes place you get
you get lashes for לא יקח lo yikach because the פסוק pasuk
actually says shall not marry. The פסוק pasuk by all the עריות,
arayos, it says right about like לא תקרב לגלות ערוה, lo tikrav
legalos ervah, it all talks about the act of intercourse. By כהנים
Kohanim it's always לא יקח lo yikach לא יקח, lo yikach do
not marry. So all along we've been focusing like it seems like
the act of sex is the prohibition, but now we're going to
really ask that question.
So אביי Abaye says when you marry you transgress לא יקח lo
yikach and when you actually have sex, that's the לא יחלל lo
yechalel we've been talking about until now. Now רש"י Rashi explains that
אביי Abaye does not mean that the act of קידושין kiddushin itself
you get lashes. We have never said the act of קידושין kiddushin
you get lashes, we've always been focusing on the act of sex,
but what אביי Abaye means is conceptually when there's קידושין kiddushin followed
by sex, so קידושין kiddushin that's followed by sex, one set of
lashes is for the קידושין, kiddushin, one set of lashes is for
the לא יחלל. lo yechalel. All right, so conceptually there's a prohibition
on marriage, which you only get lashes for with the sex that
follows marriage, and then there is another prohibition on לא יחלל. lo
yechalel. This again, the focus on לא יחלל lo yechalel for רש"י
Rashi is talking about all כהנים Kohanim and for רמב"ם Rambam is
talking about כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and אלמנה, almanah, so keep that
in mind, we'll get back to that. Okay רבא אמר: Rava amar:
בעל לוקה לא בעל אינו לוקה משום דכתיב לא יקח ולא יחלל.
Ba'al loke lo ba'al eino loke mishum d'ksiv lo yikach velo yechalel.
Wait, excuse me, I apologize. I misstated אביי, Abaye, I ran ahead
into רבא. Rava. Let's do that again. Okay, אביי Abaye is what
he sounds like. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: קידש לוקה בעל לוקה קידש
לוקה משום לא יקח בעל לוקה משום לא יחלל. Kidesh loke ba'al
loke kidesh loke mishum lo yikach ba'al loke mishum lo yechalel. So
I'm sorry, I ran ahead into רבא. Rava. So אביי Abaye says
exactly what it sounds like. No, you actually get lashes for the
act of קידושין, kiddushin, even though we haven't been saying any of
that until now, and maybe we're talking specifically about a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and an אלמנה, almanah, but anyway
lashes for לא יקח, lo yikach, separate set of lashes for the
actual sex for לא יחלל. lo yechalel. רבא Rava says and this
is what I was saying before, בעל לוקה לא בעל אינו לוקה.
Ba'al loke lo ba'al eino loke. When you actually have the sex
that follows, then you get the lashes for לא יקח lo yikach
and לא יחלל, lo yechalel, but not for just the קידושין kiddushin
itself. משום דכתיב לא יקח ולא יחלל מה טעם לא יקח משום
לא יחלל. Mishum d'ksiv lo yikach velo yechalel mah ta'am lo yikach
mishum lo yechalel. Okay. That the only time you transgress לא יקח
lo yikach is when it leads to the potential of לא יחלל
lo yechalel when actually it is followed by sex. ומודה אביי במחזיר
גרושתו שאם קידש ולא בעל שאינו לוקה. U'modeh Abaye b'machazir gerushaso she'im
kidesh velo ba'al she'eino loke. But אביי Abaye will agree that in
the case of a man who remarries his divorced wife after she's
been married to another man and gets divorced from him, that's מחזיר
גרושתו, machazir gerushaso, that in that case actually, there he agrees that
only when there is sex that follows the remarrying. Because why? Because
it says לקחתה להיות לו לאשה אמר רחמנא, Lakachtah lihyos lo l'ishah
amar rachmana, that he may not go back and remarry her to
be as a wife, meaning and that means to actually be intimate
and have sex. והא ליכא, Veha leika, and you don't have that.
Now,
so
taken on the face of it, right, it seems
like
everybody agrees to the idea introduced earlier that sex itself is לא
יחלל. lo yechalel. So the sex with a woman that's forbidden is
לא יחלל, lo yechalel, and that has nothing to do with marriage.
And the question is how do you understand the Torah's prohibition of
marriage? אביי Abaye understands it as a
standalone לא יקח, lo yikach, and רבא Rava understands it as a
לא יקח lo yikach that has,
you know, frames the לא יחלל lo yechalel so you'll only transgress
marriage or that leads into the לא יחלל, lo yechalel, you'll only
transgress marriage when it is followed by sex. So that's the debate.
Let's go ahead and now look, so now we've looked at the
question about marriage by itself before sex, אביי Abaye says yes lashes,
רבא Rava says no. Sex after marriage, both of them say yes,
אביי Abaye says one, רבא Rava says two. And now we have
to ask about, you know, the one thing we haven't addressed,
which is sex without marriage. So let's take a look.
ומודה רבא בכהן גדול באלמנה שאם בעל ולא קידש שלוקה, U'modeh Rava
b'Kohen Gadol b'almanah she'im ba'al velo kidesh she'loke,
that actually... just the ביאה biah you get lashes. Why? ולא יחלל
זרעו בעמיו אמר רחמנא והרי הוא חילל V'lo yechalel zaro b'amav amar
rachmana v'harei hu chillel
because there it says he shall not be מחלל mechallel her and
he was, he did, was מחלל mechallel because that act made her
into a חללה. chalalah. ושניהם מודים במחזיר גרושתו שאם בעל ולא קידש
אינו לוקה דרך ליקוחים אסרה תורה. V'shneihem modim b'machzir grushaso she'im ba'al
v'lo kiddesh eino loke derech likuchim asra torah.
But they also both agree that when it comes to this מחזיר
גרושתו, machzir grushaso, there remember the תורה Torah said לקחתה להיות לו
לאשה. likachtah lihyos lo l'ishah. So אביי Abaye who normally says marriage
by itself, he says להיות לו לאשה lihyos lo l'ishah says no,
in this case by מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso it has to be
marriage plus sex. רבא Rava who normally says, you know, who says
that there are cases where it's just about sex, like לא יחלל,
lo yechalel, here he would agree that no, here though, you know,
marriage is definitely necessary, he says לקחתה להיות לו לאשה. likachtah lihyos
lo l'ishah. So everybody agrees with there you need both. So let's
pull back and say that again. Okay. So for the case of,
let's start actually with the case of מחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso.
מחזיר גרושתו Machzir grushaso is you need both marriage and sex. Any
one by itself would not be it. Marriage did not because it
doesn't say לא יקח, lo yikach, it says לא ישוב לקחתה להיות
לו לאשה. lo yashuv likachtah lihyos lo l'ishah. So it's not just
the marriage, it's marriage plus the sex. Not the sex alone because
it's all talks about לקחתה likachtah in the context of marriage. So
everybody agrees that by מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso you need both marriage
and sex.
כהן גדול באלמנה, Kohen gadol b'almanah, well you know, which is what
we're talking about, just the sex is a problem, לא יחלל. lo
yechalel. אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both agree that just the sex
is a problem, לא יחלל. lo yechalel. Just the marriage, אביי Abaye
says that's a problem, לא יקח. lo yikach. רבא Rava says no,
that's only a problem when it's going to lead to sex. Okay.
So for אביי, Abaye,
forgetting מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso where you need both, for אביי, Abaye,
marriage by itself is a problem, לא יקח, lo yikach, marriage plus
sex,
לא יחלל, lo yechalel, or sex, לא יחלל. lo yechalel. רבא, Rava,
marriage by itself is not a problem until there's sex. Sex by
itself is a problem. All right.
What emerges from all of this is that it sounds like even
though the תורה Torah says לא יקח, lo yikach, which would suggest
that there's just an איסור issur of marriage,
that assuming we פוסקן pasken like רבא, Rava, that won't be the
case. Marriage you won't transgress until you have sex. The flip side
of that is, what if you're having sex without marriage? From a
simple reading of the תורה, Torah, that wouldn't be a problem. The
תורה Torah says it's a problem of marriage. But it seems that
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both agree that לא יחלל lo yechalel
forbids sex by itself. Why am I saying all of this? And
I apologize if I've confused you all a little bit there.
Because רמב"ם'ס Rambam's position is that all of this is limited to
a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. And רמב"ם Rambam himself says, remember we
said that earlier at the beginning when רב יהודה Rav Yehudah introduced
this idea, and רמב"ם Rambam says that it's by a כהן גדול
kohen gadol where it says לא יחלל lo yechalel and sex by
itself is forbidden. And when it comes to a כהן הדיוט, kohen
hedyot, you always need לא יקח. lo yikach. The prohibition is always
about marriage. And this is very relevant because, you know, there are
times and there's whole issues about a כהן kohen marrying a גרושה
grushah and so on, and you try to see maybe she's not
really a גרושה, grushah, maybe he's not really a כהן, kohen, try
to sort of figure out ways to deal with it. And one
thing that פוסקים poskim sort of keep in mind is that if
there's no קידושין kiddushin with this woman of a כהן kohen and
a גרושה, grushah, that according to רמב"ם, Rambam, there actually would not
be a prohibition. The whole prohibition is in the context of קידושין.
kiddushin. So now the kids would still be חללים, challalim, she would
still become a חללה, chalalah, all of that would be true. So
the kids would not be כהנים. kohanim. But in terms of a
prohibition, רמב"ם Rambam says goes back to the לא יקח lo yikach
of the פסוק. pasuk. So
once again רב יהודה Rav Yehudah introduces, and apologize if it got
a little muddy in the middle, but let's try it again. רב
יהודה Rav Yehudah introduces the idea that לא יחלל lo yechalel is
a prohibition just of sex and he says you get two lashes
for the marriage and for the sex. Fine. Okay. רמב"ם Rambam says
that's limited to כהן גדול. kohen gadol. רש"י Rashi says that that
applies to all כהנים. kohanim.
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava we have just seen debate, whether marriage
by itself is a problem or only marriage followed by the sex.
That's within the לא יקח. lo yikach. Everybody seemed to say the
sex by itself was a problem. But רמב"ם Rambam says again that
idea that the sex by itself is a problem is just כהן
גדול. kohen gadol.
A normal כהן kohen you need the לא יקח, lo yikach, לא
יקח lo yikach followed by sex but you need the לא יקח.
lo yikach. Okay. Hope you all got that. Let's continue in the
גמרא. Gemara. תניא. Tanya. רבי יהודה אומר בת גר
זכר כבת חלל. Rabbi Yehuda omer bas ger zachar kebas challal.
So now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that a, going back to
the משנה, Mishnah, that the same way the daughter of a חלל
challal is a חללה, challalah, the daughter of a גר ger is
a חללה, challalah, which is a big issue in terms of you
know making in terms of women that would be then forbidden to
כהנים. kohanim. And also it will come out that the daughter of
a non-Jew man is a חללה challalah according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. We do not פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. תניא,
Tanya, we return to a ברייתא. Beraita. רבי יהודה אומר בת גר
זכר כבת חלל, Rabbi Yehuda omer bas ger zachar kebas challal, כבת
חלל זכר. kebas challal zachar.
The daughter of a male גר ger is like the daughter of
a male חלל challal and she is a חללה. challalah. ודן הוא,
Vedin hu, and you can learn it out logically.
מה חלל שבא מטיפה כשירה בתו פסולה, Mah challal sheba mitipa kesheira
bito pesula,
a חלל challal that was born Jewish, his daughter is invalid, is
a חללה. challalah. גר שבא מטיפה פסולה, Ger sheba mitipa pesula, a
גר ger that came from a you know a literally an invalid
drop of semen, meaning a גר ger that was not born Jewish,
אינו דין שבתו פסולה, eino din shebito pesula, certainly his daughter should
be invalid. Which is a bizarre הוה אמינא, hava amina, whoever says
it has to do with whether you were born Jewish or not?
Okay. I mean חלל challal has a problem, a גר ger doesn't.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, מה לחלל שכן יצירתו בעבירה, mah
lechallal shekein yetziraso ba'aveira, exactly that. A חלל challal maybe he makes
his daughter a problem because a חלל challal was born in sin,
right? He was born through through a forbidden act of sex between
a כהן kohen and a woman a כהן kohen is forbidden to.
כהן גדול באלמנה יוכיח. Kohen gadol be'almanah yochiach. No, I'll prove to
you that that's not necessarily the case because what if you have
a כהן גדול kohen gadol and an אלמנה almanah שאין יצירתה בעבירה
בתו פסולה. she'ein yetzirasa ba'aveira bito pesula. So in that case,
so if a כהן גדול kohen gadol has sex with an אלמנה,
almanah, he makes her into a חללה. challalah. So a חללה challalah
does not only come from somebody who was created through sin, meaning
there are two ways a woman could become a חללה: challalah: born
from a חלל challal and through sex with a כהן kohen she
is forbidden to. So the גמרא Gemara says you cannot say that
a חללה challalah status is limited to a case when you start
with something someone that was that was you know that was created
in sin, which is the case of a חלל, challal, okay? Because
a woman can become a חללה challalah even not related to somebody
who was created in sin when she had sex with a man
who was forbidden to her, a כהן kohen who was forbidden to
her. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מה לכהן גדול באלמנה
שכן ביאתו בעבירה. mah lekohen gadol be'almanah shekein biaso ba'aveira. No, but
at least there there is another problem, the sin is in the
act of sex. So a woman who is a חללה challalah comes
from one way or another some act of forbidden sex, either she
is born from a male חלל challal who was created through a
forbidden act of sex, or she herself participated in a forbidden act
of sex. Okay, so right now it is saying ah, but neither
one those are two different reasons. So somehow
the the you know we're going to try to throw גר ger
in there even though גר ger seems completely unrelated. So the גמרא
Gemara says
חלל יוכיח. challal yochiach. Okay, but you can't say it is the
act of sex that's the problem because in the case of a
חלל challal with a ישראלית, Yisraelis, the daughter of a חלל, challal,
there was no forbidden act of sex, he was created in sin
but he himself didn't engage in a forbidden act of sex. וחזר
הדין, Vechazar hadin, and it goes back. לא ראי זה כראי זה
וכו׳ הצד השוה שבהן. Lo rei zeh kerei zeh etc. hatzad hashaveh
shebahen. One is not like the other. The common denominator שאינן ברוב
הקהל, she'einan berov hakahal, they're not like the normal population, which is
like such a broad generic thing. One person is on the margins
because they were created in sin, the חלל, challal, and then his
daughter is going to be even though she was not involved in
a sinful there was no act of forbidden sex in the giving
birth of her in the conceiving of the daughter, that creates a
חללה. challalah. Okay, he's on the margins for that reason. The woman
who is now engaged in an act of forbidden sex, she is
not the majority of the population. So one or the other of
those are not the normal quote-unquote majority population because of some element
of sin. Okay, and therefore also throw in גר ger who wasn't
born Jewish. אף אני אביא את הגר שאינו ברוב הקהל ובתו פסולה,
Af ani avi es hager she'eino berov hakahal uvito pesula, which is
like just so bizarre, like completely like unrelated, you know? So the
גמרא Gemara says מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן יש בהן צד עבירה.
mah lehatzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yesh bahen tzad aveira. And the גמרא
Gemara says nah, and besides that it is just way too generic
to be meaningful. It says there is a much better way of
categorizing both of the ways a woman can become a חללה challalah
is that there is some עבירה aveira that is involved. Okay, that
obviously is not relevant to a גר. ger. לא תימא Lo seima
so the גמרא Gemara concedes that point. Fine. לא תימא כהן גדול
באלמנה יוכיח אלא אימא מצרי ראשון יוכיח. Lo seima kohen gadol be'almanah
yochiach ela eima mitzri rishon yochiach. Let's fine, let's try this case.
Let's try the case of a first-generation מצרי. mitzri. So that type
of a person, this is not a חללה challalah status, he has
sex with a first-generation מצרית, mitzris, nobody is doing a sin, nobody
is being born in sin, and nevertheless the child of that, a
second-generation מצרי, mitzri, is forbidden, you know is forbidden. Not just to
a כהן, kohen, it is forbidden to everybody. מה
למצרי שכן אינו ראוי Mah lemitzri shekein eino ra'uy
so therefore that just but it shows you, you see? that different
type of problematic people
can be forbidden to כהנים kohanim or to some people. I mean,
it's just so broad here, it's not even meaningful. מה למצרי שכן
Mah l'mitzri she-kein says the גמרא, Gemara, שכן אינו ראוי לבוא בקהל.
she-kein eino ra'uy lavo b'kahal. No,
that's, there you're dealing with somebody that is completely, like, not able
to marry, which doesn't, isn't true about a חלל, chalal, and isn't
true about any of these other people that are able to marry.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, חלל יוכיח. chalal yochi'ach. Oh, but
it's not about not being able to marry at all, because there
are other people that can't marry a כהן. kohen. וחזר הדין לא
ראי זה כראי זה הצד השוה שבהן שאינן ברוב קהל ובתן פסולה.
V'chazar hadin lo re'i zeh k're'i zeh hatzad hashaveh shebahen she'einan b'rov
kahal uvitan psulah. Okay,
but now you've got all of them thrown together. So the חלל,
chalal, the חללה chalalah that was born through an act of from
a חלל, chalal, the חלל chalal that was made a חללה chalalah
through a sex with a כהן, kohen, and the מצרי שני, mitzri
sheini, and all these people somehow are forbidden, although two to כהנים
kohanim and one to everybody. And therefore, that will teach me that
the daughter of a גר ger is also forbidden. If you can't
follow the logic, that makes two of us. Okay, אף אני אביא
את הגר שאינו ברוב קהל ובתו פסולה, Af ani avi et hager
she'eino b'rov kahal uvito psulah, he's not the majority of the population
and his daughter is פסולה. psulah. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן פסולין בביאתן. Mah l'hatzad hashaveh shebahen she-kein
psulin b'vi'atan. All of these people will make a woman פסולה, psulah,
right, will make a woman a, in some way or another. A
חלל chalal will make a woman into a חללה chalalah and a
מצרי mitzri could make a woman into a זונה, zonah, forbidden act
of sex. So all of these, they're starting with people that are
problematic in some way. A גר ger starts completely not problematic, which
is what's so troubling about just throwing גר ger here. Like you
gotta have a predisposition to think גר ger is a problem, right?
Cuz all these are problematic in one way or another. לרבי יהודה
גר נמי פוסל בביאתו. L'Rabbi Yehuda ger nami posel b'vi'ato. And Rabbi
Yehuda would say, you know what, I'll say the same thing. Once
I'm gonna say that a גר ger will make his daughter into
a חללה, chalalah, I will also say that a גר ger will
make a normal woman into a חללה chalalah as well. Okay, ומייתי
לה במה הצד מהאי דינא, umayti lah b'mah hatzad meihai dina, the
same way he makes some גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah here to, or
whatever, some צד השוה tzad hashaveh in order to say that a
child of a גר ger is a חללה, chalalah, female child, he
will also say a woman a גר ger has sex with becomes
a חללה chalalah as well. So this is like deeply, deeply problematic
because it's like this category is so broad and it obviously starts
by problematizing גר ger which allows you to include גר ger in
it. And then it means that for Rabbi Yehuda, a גר ger
like is supposed to be part of the community, but then any
woman he has sex with, she becomes a חללה, chalalah, if he
ever dies, can't marry a כהן, kohen, the daughter is a חללה,
chalalah, like always remains second-class status and not fit for
כהנים. kohanim. So it's a very problematic position, we don't פוסקן pasken
it. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר גר. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer
ger. So now we have the other position in the משנה, mishnah,
which is Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Where he says that only the
offspring of a גר ger and a גיורת giyoret is invalid for
a כהן. kohen. Okay, and maybe that's because the same a גיורת
giyoret is invalid for a כהן, kohen, the daughter of a גר
ger and a גיורת giyoret is invalid for a כהן kohen as
well. All right, so let's take a look. תניא, Tanya, but we
don't פוסקן pasken that either. תניא רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר גיורת
פחותה מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד כשירה לכהונה. Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai omer giyoret p'chutah mibat shalosh shanim v'yom echad k'sherah l'khunah. Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai says if a woman converted less than three years
old, she's כשרה kosher to כהונה, kehunah, because he is focusing, because
we haven't dealt with the question about what is the problem for
a גר ger and a כהן kohen to begin with, and he
is going to focus, we're going to see, on the fact that
she might have had sex
when she was a non-Jew. רש"י Rashi actually said that way at
the beginning, at the beginning on a משנה, mishnah, that a גיורת
giyoret is a problem because it's a חזקת זונה, chezkat zonah, because
you assume she had sex. But so that's Rabbi seems to be
Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai's position, גיורת פחותה מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד
כשירה לכהונה. giyoret p'chutah mibat shalosh shanim v'yom echad k'sherah l'khunah. And
therefore if she was converted less than three years old, she's כשרה.
kosher. שנאמר וכל הטף בנשים החיו לכם. shene'emar v'chol hataf banashim hachayu
lachem. בלא פנחס היו עמהם, B'lo Pinchas hayu imahem, so you can
keep the women from Midian less than three years old. פנחס היו
עמהם, Pinchas hayu imahem, and you can keep for yourselves, meaning to
be wives, and Pinchas was included, so you see that that's okay.
ורבנן החיו לכם לעבדים ולשפחות. V'rabbanan hachayu lachem l'avadim ul'shfachot. And the
rabbis say no, no, no, it means that you can keep them
as servants, as slaves, it does not mean that you can marry
them. So
וכולן
מקרא אחד דרשו. v'chulan mikra echad darshu. Now all of these different
positions about a גר, ger, and now we're going to have a
much better דרשה drashah than the one we had before, about the
problem of an offspring of a גר ger or a גר, ger,
is all based on the following פסוק pasuk by יחזקאל. Yechezkel. אלמנה
וגרושה לא יקחו להם לנשים כי אם בתולות מזרע בית ישראל. Almanah
u'grushah lo yikchu lahem l'nashim ki im betulot mizerah beit Yisrael. An
אלמנה almanah and גרושה grushah they cannot marry for wives, except rather
only the virgins from the house of בית ישראל. Beit Yisrael. Now
this is very difficult because it's talking about normal כהנים, kohanim, but
this seems to be what's traits about a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
because it speaks about not marrying an אלמנה almanah and only marrying
a בתולה. betulah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with
this. רב יהודה הסבר עד. Rav Yehudah hasvar ad. Rabbi
Yehuda now we're gonna have a much better דרשה *drasha* for Rabbi
Yehuda who has a problem with the daughter of a גר *ger*
and he's going to say עד דאיכא כל זרע מישראל *ad de'ika
kol zera miYisrael*. So he's going to read בתולות מזרע בית ישראל
mizera beit Yisrael *betulot mizera beit Yisrael* like ignore sort of the
בתולות *betulot* part and basically say that that is, you know, that
that it has to come from Jewish seed and from Jewish seed
here meaning focusing on seed, the man. Okay, so the father has
to be Jewish. So actually a Jewish, a naturally born Jew plus
a גיורת *giyoret*, the child would be okay. But a גר *ger*
plus a naturally born Jewish woman, that is not מזרע בית ישראל
*mizera beit Yisrael* and therefore it's invalid. So at least that's much,
much better than before, which just fundamentally problematized everything. Here it is
saying, I mean the result is still the same, but he's not
saying the woman becomes פסול *pasul*. Here he's saying that it has
to be from Jewish seed to marry a כהן *kohen*, male Jewish
seed. That's Rabbi
Yehuda. Not saying that she's a חללה *chalalah* or anything necessarily like
that. Okay,
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov סבר *savar* מזרע ואפילו מקצת זרע *mizera va'afilo
miktzat zera*. No, some of the seed has to be Jewish, either
the mother or the father. As long as she has a naturally
born Jewish mother or Jewish father, she's okay. If both parents, however,
are גרים *gerim*, then the child is still, is, is going to
be forbidden. Rabbi Yosei סבר *savar* משנזרעו בישראל *mishenizre'u beYisrael*. And Rabbi
Yosei,
who says that, you know, even the child of a גר *ger*
and a גיורת *giyoret* are fine, says as long as she was
conceived amongst people who were Jews. It does not have to be,
you know, so therefore the only problem is somebody who actually was
מגייר *megayer*, the גיורת *giyoret* herself. Okay, but somebody who was conceived
once the parents, both parents, what, you know, the when, when the
mother, you know, but even by a גר *ger* and a גיורת
*giyoret*, since they were both Jewish at the time, it is not
going to be a problem. So basically what we have here is,
and this is really, really critical in understanding the problem of a
גיורת *giyoret*. Is a גיורת *giyoret* a problem of a concern of
having had sex when she was not Jewish, which is, sounds like,
you know, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, which is why he allows her
less than three years old? Or is it having nothing to do
with the concern of having sex? Is it about the fact that
there's some concept of מזרע בית ישראל *mizera beit Yisrael*, of a
Jewish seed? Alright, and that seems to certainly be this דרשה *drasha*.
Of course, this דרשה *drasha* is not a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in
the Torah, so there are some that understand that this whole second
approach based on זרע בית ישראל *zera beit Yisrael* is דרבנן derabbanan
*derabanan*. That's a fascinating question if a גיורת *giyoret* for כהן *kohen*
is a problem of דאורייתא *de'oraita* or דרבנן *derabanan*. But following this
פסוק *pasuk* of יחזקאל Yechezkel *Yechezkel*, that it's more of not of
a concern of sex, but מזרע בית ישראל *mizera beit Yisrael*, you
could have a couple of reads. It could mean בית ישראל *Beit
Yisrael* could be read restrictively, meaning naturally born Jew. That's the first
two reads of it. And then it's read either the father has
to be a naturally born Jew,
or the one of the parents has to be a naturally born
Jew. Okay, that would explain why a גר *ger*, a normal גר
*ger* is no good, because parents weren't Jews. And it would also
explain why, you know, possibly the offspring of a גר *ger* would
not be a problem. That's if you read that. And the third
read of Rabbi Yosei is בית ישראל *Beit Yisrael* just means not
naturally born Jew, but Jewish. And therefore anybody born once somebody has,
you know, to the child of anybody converted is not a problem.
The only problem is somebody born not Jewish or conceived not Jewish.
Big difference there. Okay, and Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai סבר *savar* משנזרעו
בתוליה בישראל *mishenizre'u betuloha beYisrael*. And Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says somebody
who became a virgin while she was Jewish, so she has to
convert less than three, because it's understood that the hymen grows in
at the age of three, and therefore somebody who became three years
old when she was Jewish, only somebody who converted under the age
of three. Alright, so to wrap up what we have seen here
is a lot of really important
stuff. And we've seen a whole question at least the beginning of
ע"ח ע"א *Ayin Chet Amud Aleph* about whether sex itself there's a
prohibition of not only גרושה ואלמנה *grusha ve'almanah* but of making the
woman into a חללה *chalalah*, which focuses on the act of sex.
Okay, that's what Rabbi Yehuda introduces and then that leads to a
whole question about קידושין *kiddushin* before the sex. Abaye says קידושין *kiddushin*
itself is a problem. Rava only says with the sex.
Sex without the קידושין *kiddushin*, that seems everybody says is a problem
of לא יחלל *lo yechalel*, the idea that Rabbi Yehuda introduced. But
Rambam says no, that's only by a כהן גדול *kohen gadol*. That
actually by a כהן הדיוט *kohen hedyot*, it has to be always
with the קידושין *kiddushin*. It starts with לא יקח *lo yikach*, there's
no separate לא יחלל *lo yechalel* except for a כהן גדול *kohen
gadol*. Very important, that position of Rambam. And then we have seen
here, very important, this question about a גר *ger*, whether the, why
is a גר *ger* a problem, is it Is it because of
a concern of sex or is it because of which might be
a דאורייתא of זונה zonah or a חשש דאורייתא chashash de'oraita of
זונה, zonah, but then you could make distinctions under three years, other
possible ways of making distinctions or is it because of this פסוק
of יחזקאל which might be דרבנן which is based on מזרע בית
ישראל and that could lead to a whole range of positions that
either the father has to be a naturally born Jew or one
of the parents has to be a naturally born Jew
or
as long as the parents are Jewish even if they were converted
Jews it's always going to be fine, the only problem is if
the person was born not Jewish or conceived not Jewish, that's the
way we פסקן, pasken, and then finally the position of רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai which is it matters whether it
was converted less than three or more than three years old. Okay,
we will end here.